Guide to the William Holland Thomas papers, 1814-1898
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William Holland Thomas papers 1814-1898
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Thomas, William Holland, 1805-1893
10 linear feet Extent: 2789 Items
Indian agent, lawyer, and trader, of Haywood Co., N.C. Correspondence, account books, day books, ledgers, and other papers, relating to Thomas' life in western North Carolina, the removal of the Cherokee Indians and the status of those who remained, Civil War fighting in east Tennessee, postwar administration of Indian affairs, and his private business operations as a trader among the Cherokees. Includes records of Thomas' five stores in Haywood and Cherokee counties, and business correspondence and accounts of Thomas' son, also William Holland Thomas, a merchant and farmer of Jackson County, N.C. Other subjects include railroads and roads in North Carolina.
RL.01290
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The William Holland Thomas papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library between 1938 and 1952.
Biographical Note
William Holland Thomas (1805-1893) was an Indian agent, lawyer, and trader, of Haywood Co., N.C.
Collection Overview
Collection contains letters and papers of William H. Thomas (1805-1893), lawyer, Indian agent and trader, and colonel in the Confederate Army, concerning his life in western North Carolina, the removal of the Cherokee Indians and the status of those who remained in North Carolina, the building of roads and railroads, fighting during the Civil War in East Tennessee, postwar administration of Indian affairs, and private business of Thomas. There are also account books, day books, and ledgers showing a record of goods bought and sold in Thomas's five stores in Haywood and Cherokee counties. Included also are business correspondence and miscellaneous accounts, 1875-1890, of his son, William Holland Thomas, Jr., merchant and farmer of Jackson County, North Carolina. The library also holds microfilm, 2 reels, William Holland Thomas papers, 1820-1931, in the possession of James R. Thomas, Waynesville, North Carolina.
Subject Headings
Cherokee County (N.C.) -- History; Cherokee Indians -- Government relations; Cherokee Indians -- Legal status, laws, etc.; Farmers -- North Carolina -- Jackson County; General stores -- North Carolina -- Cherokee County; General stores -- North Carolina -- Haywood County; Haywood County (N.C.) -- History; Indians of North America -- North Carolina; Jackson County (N.C.) -- History; Merchants -- North Carolina -- Haywood County; Railroads -- North Carolina; Roads -- North Carolina; Tennessee -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
Contents of Collection
- William Holland Thomas papers, 1814-1898, (6 boxes; 71 volumes)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1814-1842, (7 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1843-1850, (7 folders) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1851-1864, (7 folders) (Box 3)
  - Correspondence and papers, 1865-1899 and undated, (6 folders) (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and papers, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Receipts and accounts, (5 folders) (Box 5)
  - Receipts and clippings, (6 folders) (Box 6)
  - Preservation copy of Supplementary Report of Cherokee Indians Remaining in N.C., (1 folder) (Box 6)
  - Account Book, 1834-1836 (Box 6, Volume F:3849)
    Scott's Creek, Haywood County, N.C.
  - Accounts, 1835-1839 (Box 6, Volume F:3850)
  - Accounts, Records of Indebtedness and Inventory of Goods, 1836-1853 (Box 6, Volume L:3851)
  - Account Book, 1836-1841 (Box 6, Volume M:3852)
    Haywood County, N.C.
  - Account Book: Inventory, Order Book, Notes and Accounts Due, Misc. Accounts, 1836-1841 (Box 6, Volume L:3853)
    Indiantown, [Quallatown], Haywood County, N.C.
  - Account Book, 1837 (Box 6, Volume S:3854)
  - Accounts, 1837-1838 (Box 6, Volume F:3855)
  - Account Book, 1838 (Box 6, Volume M:3856)
  - Diary and Account Book, 1839-1841 (Box 6, Volume S:3857)
  - Accounts, 1845-1849 (List of goods sold); Day Book, 1850-1851 (Box 6, Volume L:3858)
    Quallatown, Haywood County, N.C.
  - Account Book, 1849-1850 (Box 6, Volume L:3859)
  - Account Book, 1864 (Box 6, Volume S:3860)
  - Account Book, 1878 (Box 6, Volume S:3861)
    Junaluska, Jackson County, N.C.
  - Accounts, 1880 (Box 6, Volume F:3862)
  - Accounts of Indebtedness, 1839-1842 (Box 6, Volume L:3863)
    Murphy, Cherokee County, N.C.
  - Cash Book, 1837-1872 (Box 6, Volume M:3864)
    Calhoun, Tenn.
  - Cash Book, 1838 (Box 6, Volume F:3865)
  - Collection Book, 1834-1838 (Box 6, Volume F:3866)
  - Collection and Receipt Book, 1875-1880 (Box 6, Volume L:3867)
  - Day Book, 1832-1833 (Box 6, Volume F:3868)
  - Day Book, 1833-1834 (Box 6, Volume F:3869)
  - Day Book, 1834-1835 (Box 6, Volume F:3870)
  - Day Book, 1836-1838 (Box 6, Volume F:3871)
  - Day Book, 1836-1845 (Box 6, Volume F:3872)
  - Day Book, 1837 (Box 6, Volume F:3873)
  - Day Book, 1837-1839 (Box 6, Volume F:3874)
  - Day Book, 1839 (Box 6, Volume L:3875)
  - Day Book, 1839-1840 (Box 6, Volume L:3876)
  - Day Book, 1839-1840 (Box 6, Volume F:3877)
  - [unidentified volume] (Box 6, Volume L:3878)
  - Day Book, 1840-1841 (Box 6, Volume L:3879)
  - Day Book, 1840-1843 (Box 6, Volume F:3880)
  - Day Book, 1841-1842 (Box 6, Volume L:3881)
  - Day Book, 1845-1848 (Box 6, Volume L:3882)
  - Day Book, 1848-1850 (Box 6, Volume L:3883)
  - Day Book, 1851 (Box 6, Volume L:3884)
  - Day Book, 1851-1853 (Box 6, Volume L:3885)
  - Day Book, 1852-1854 (Box 6, Volume L:3886)
    Fort Montgomery, Cherokee County, N.C.
  - Day Book, 1853-1854 (Box 6, Volume L:3887)
  - Day Book, 1853-1854 (Box 6, Volume L:3888)
  - Day Book, 1854-1855 (Box 6, Volume F:3889)
  - Day Book, 1854-1857 (Box 6, Volume L:3890)
  - Day Book, 1855-1856 (Box 6, Volume F:3891)
  - Day Book, 1856-1857 (Box 6, Volume F:3892)
  - Day Book, 1858-1863 (Box 6, Volume F:3893)
  - Depositions, legal notes, etc., 1828-1843 (Box 6, Volume M:3894)
  - Diary and Account Book, 1840 (Box 6, Volume S:3895)
  - Index to ledger, 1847 (Box 6, Volume ff:3896)
  - Indian Book, 1837 (Box 6, Volume ff:3897)
  - Indian Book, 1857 (Box 6, Volume S:3898)
  - Invoice Book, 1838; Day Book, 1840-1842 (Box 6, Volume F:3899)
  - Journal, 1836-1837; Day Book, 1838 (Box 6, Volume F:3900)
  - Journal and Day Book, 1840-1844 (Box 6, Volume F:3901)
  - Land Book, 1837 (Box 6, Volume F:3902)
  - Land Book, 1838-1853 (Box 6, Volume F:3903)
  - Ledger, 1833-1834 (Box 6, Volume ff:3904)
  - Ledger, 1835-1837 (Box 6, Volume F:3905)
  - Ledger, 1836-1838 (Box 6, Volume F:3906)
  - Ledger, 1836-1845 (Box 6, Volume F:3907)
  - Ledger, 1837-1847 (Box 6, Volume F:3908)
  - Ledger, 1839-1844 (Box 6, Volume L:3909)
  - Ledger [New Firm], 1839-1843 (Box 6, Volume F:3910)
    Cherokee County, N.C.
  - Ledger and Day Book, 1839-1841 (Box 6, Volume F:3911)
  - Ledger, 1839-1845 (Box 6, Volume F:3912)
  - Ledger, 1840-1845 (Box 6, Volume F:3913)
  - Ledger and Indian Accounts, 1840-1858 (Box 6, Volume F:3914)
  - Ledger (Postage Accounts), 1844-1845 (Box 6, Volume M:3915)
  - Ledger, 1845-1848 (Box 6, Volume F:3916)
  - Ledger (White Customers), 1847-1855 (Box 6, Volume F:3917)
  - Letterbook, 1835-1842 (Box 6, Volume L:3918)
  - Letterbook and Accounts, 1838-1845 (Box 6, Volume L:3919)
  - Letterbook, 1858 (Box 6, Volume M:3920)
  - List of White Accounts, Notes, Judgements, Etc., 1849-1867 (Box 6, Volume M:3921)
  - Miscellaneous Accounts, 1874 (Box 6, Volume S:3922)
  - Rail Road Book, 1854-1855 (Box 6, Volume S:3923)
  - Register of Reservations Under the Cherokee Treaty of 1817 (Box 6, Volume M:3924)
    North Carolina and Tennessee
  - Scrapbook, 1852-1888 (Box 6, Volume F:3925)
    Jackson County, N.C.
  - Scrapbook, circa 1890 (Box 6, Volume L:3926)
    Waynesville, N.C.
  - Supplementary Report of Cherokee Indians Remaining in N.C., 1835 (Box 6, Volume L:3927)
  - Turnpike Records, 1859 (Box 6, Volume M:3928)